Finding aid to the Vernon Gotwals Papers CA.MS.00360
Smith College Archives
Vernon Gotwals Papers
1810-1984
Smith College Archives
Gotwals, Vernon
CA.MS.00360
1.25 linear feet (3 containers)
Professor of Music. Collection contains biographical material, research notes, correspondence, and songs.
Biographical / Historical
Vernon Detweiler Gotwals came to Smith College in 1952 as an instructor in music and College organist. He earned his AB degree at Amherst College, and an MFA from Princeton University in 1951. He progressively rose in the ranks and was appointed a full professor in 1966. He also served as Secretary of the Faculty (1960-1963), and Chair of the Department of Music beginning in 1962.
Gotwals most celebrated work was on Haydn, Joseph Haydn: Eighteenth Century Gentleman and Genius published by the University of Wisconsin Press in 1963. He produced numerous scholarly monographs, articles, and reviews ranging from Haydn to Bach, the relationship of music to church liturgy, and folk songs and women's voices. He taught courses in harmony and counterpoint, and gave organ lessons to a countless number of students.
In 1984 Gotwals retired from Smith College and enjoyed emeritus status. He spent the remaining years in Deer Isle, Maine with his wife and family. Gotwals died on January 12, 2002.
Scope and Contents
The Vernon Gotwals papers contain biographical information, research notes, correspondence, and published and unpublished songs relating to his work on Haydn, women's voices, folk songs, and Sophie Drinker.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Vernon Gotwals Papers were donated to the Smith College Archives after his retirement from the College in 1984. Periodic additions have been made by Gotwals and his wife, Carol Joyce Gotwals over the years. The Sophie Drinker material was transferred from the Sophia Smith Collection.
Gotwals, Vernon
- Biographical material, 1952-84 (Box 828, Folder 1)
- Publications: "Memoir by a College Organist", undated (Box 828, Folder 2)
- Publications: "Joseph Haydn: Eighteenth Century Gentleman and Genius" - Bibliography, 1963 (Box 828, Folder 3)
- Publications: "Joseph Haydn: Eighteenth Century Gentleman and Genius" - Notes to Griesinger, 1968 (Box 828, Folder 4)
- Publications: "Joseph Haydn: Eighteenth Century Gentleman and Genius" - Notes, general, 1968 (Box 828, Folder 5)
- Publications: "Mrs. Conkling's Junior Year Abroad", 1962 (Box 828, Folder 6)
- Publications: "Folksongs for Women's Voices: Arranged by Johannes Brahms" - Notes (part of the Smith College Music Archives), 1968 (Box 828, Folder 7)
- Publications: "Folksongs for Women's Voices: Arranged by Johannes Brahms" - Unpublished songs, 1968 (Box 828, Folder 8)
- Publications: "Folksongs for Women's Voices: Arranged by Johannes Brahms" - Published songs, 1968 (Box 828, Folder 9)
- Card index to Sophie Drinker folksong material, undated (Box 828, Folder 10-11)
- Transcription of "Biographical Accounts of Joseph Haydn, According to His Spoken Narration Drawn Up and Edited by Albert Christoph Dies Landscape Painter" (Vienna 1810) (Box 828.1)
- General (Box 829)